<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Software As Craft</title>
    <link>https://softwareascraft.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Software As Craft</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <managingEditor>paige.watson@softwareascraft.com (Paige)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>paige.watson@softwareascraft.com (Paige)</webMaster>
    <copyright>&lt;a href=&#34;https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CC BY-NC 4.0&lt;/a&gt;</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2023 07:30:35 -0900</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://softwareascraft.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Interviewing - Part II</title>
      <link>https://softwareascraft.com/posts/thoughtsoninterviewing-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 13 Apr 2023 07:30:35 -0900</pubDate><author>paige.watson@softwareascraft.com (Paige)</author>
      <guid>https://softwareascraft.com/posts/thoughtsoninterviewing-2/</guid>
      <description>In the [first part][thoughts-on-interviewing-1] of this series, I talked a little about how our industry interviews currently and some of the issues I have with the current process. In this post, I want to talk a little more about what we should be doing in interviews, and who we&amp;rsquo;re actually trying to hire.
First, let&amp;rsquo;s talk about what we&amp;rsquo;re trying to get out of our hiring process.
If the answer is: &amp;ldquo;A software developer&amp;rdquo; I would pose that we need to think a little deeper about what we really want out of a candidate.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Thoughts on Interviewing - Part I</title>
      <link>https://softwareascraft.com/posts/thoughtsoninterviewing-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2023 07:30:35 -0900</pubDate><author>paige.watson@softwareascraft.com (Paige)</author>
      <guid>https://softwareascraft.com/posts/thoughtsoninterviewing-1/</guid>
      <description>As a developer for over 30 years, I’ve come to realize several problems with the way we interview in the Software Development industry. Whether it’s because we don’t know how to correctly interview for a development position, or we’re not allowed to interview in the way that’s needed, it needs to change.
As a Senior-level Code Crafter, I’m finding it frustrating to interview with (and do interviews for) companies that have processes counter-intuitive to their desired outcome of hiring a great developer.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Creating a Culture of Learning</title>
      <link>https://softwareascraft.com/posts/creatingacultureoflearning/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Apr 2023 15:00:26 -0900</pubDate><author>paige.watson@softwareascraft.com (Paige)</author>
      <guid>https://softwareascraft.com/posts/creatingacultureoflearning/</guid>
      <description>Stop me if you’ve heard this before:
CFO says: &amp;ldquo;What if we pay to train our employees, and they leave the company?&amp;rdquo;
CTO says: ….
If you are in a “management” position (or if you aren’t, imagine what your manager would say), what percentage of the work week would you like your team to be learning and growing at their job?
This is how I start out my talk on creating a learning culture.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Software as Craft</title>
      <link>https://softwareascraft.com/posts/onsoftwareascraft/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 14:42:01 -0900</pubDate><author>paige.watson@softwareascraft.com (Paige)</author>
      <guid>https://softwareascraft.com/posts/onsoftwareascraft/</guid>
      <description>As A Craft I self-identify as a &amp;ldquo;Software Crafter&amp;rdquo;. I believe that the creation of software is a complex endeavor, more akin to an artists work, than that of a plumber, electrician or factory worker.
Please be cognizant that I am not putting down anyone who is employed as a plumber, electrician, factory worker, or whatever. I believe that any (and all) of these jobs can be incredibly thought and labor intensive.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Collaborative Programming... Remotely!</title>
      <link>https://softwareascraft.com/posts/collaborativeprogrammingremotely/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Apr 2023 14:56:39 -0900</pubDate><author>paige.watson@softwareascraft.com (Paige)</author>
      <guid>https://softwareascraft.com/posts/collaborativeprogrammingremotely/</guid>
      <description>One of the most active topics at meet-ups and in online discussion groups in the last few months centers around &amp;ldquo;what works&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;what doesn&amp;rsquo;t work&amp;rdquo; when collaborative programming in our new era of all remote work. Over time, the one list of &amp;ldquo;do&amp;rsquo;s&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;don&amp;rsquo;ts&amp;rdquo; that has made it&amp;rsquo;s way to the forefront of discussions is the list at remotemobprogramming.org, compiled by Simon Harrer, Jochen Christ, and Martin Huber.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Six-Minute Interview</title>
      <link>https://softwareascraft.com/posts/sixminuteinterview/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 10:32:01 -0900</pubDate><author>paige.watson@softwareascraft.com (Paige)</author>
      <guid>https://softwareascraft.com/posts/sixminuteinterview/</guid>
      <description>First, the &amp;ldquo;Why&amp;rdquo; This interview challenge is based on the six minute interview created by Llewellyn Falco.
The idea behind this challenge is not to have the candidate solve the challenge, but to get an idea of whether the candidate understands certain principles of development.
After 6 minutes, you should be able to answer several questions, with the most important being:
Do I want to see more from this candidate?</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
